Guide to the Talcott family papers, 1604-1856, 1787-1856 (bulk)
Talcott family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Talcott family papers, 1604-1856, 1787-1856 (bulk)
2087
Pruyn, Olivia S. T.,
.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diaries, legal and financial documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Journal-account book (1823) kept by George Talcott, U.S. Army Ordnance Department, while on an official surveying trip through Ohio, Kentucky, and Tennessee; thirty-six Mexican War letters; one diary of Talcott's son, Sebastian Visscher Talcott. Also, personal and business correspondence and accounts, estate settlement papers, deeds, bills, and miscellaneous papers of the related Talcott, Shearman (Sherman), Bogard, and Gibson families; fair copies of 17th and 18th century wills and inventories.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Journal-account book (1823) kept by George Talcott, U.S. Army Ordnance Department, while on an official surveying trip through Ohio, Kentucky,. and Tennessee; one letter to Talcott from Winfield Scott (1842) concerning a recently invented machine for throwing shot; thirty-six Mexican War letters, chiefly to Talcott at Washington, D.C. from Benjamin Huger, Scott's chief of ordnance, concerning the capture of Vera Cruz, the march on Mexico City, the storming of Chapultepec, and the numerous difficulties encountered on this campaign, but also from Alexander Brydie Dyer, describing the action taken to quell the Taos uprising and other events, and from Josiah Gorgas, George Douglas Ramsay, and other officers; one diary (1841-1842) of Talcott's son, Sebastian Visscher Talcott, kept during the official survey of the Northeastern boundary of the United States. Also, personal and business correspondence and accounts, estate settlement papers, deeds, bills, and miscellaneous papers of the related Talcott, Shearman (Sherman), Bogard, and Gibson families; fair copies of 17th and 18th century wills and inventories. Places represented include Braintree, Essex County, England; Glastonbury, Wethersfield, Connecticut; Albany, Canandaigua, New York City, Rochester, and Utica, New York; and Danville, Illinois.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Pruyn, Olivia S. T.,; Bogart family; Gibson family.; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866.; Sherman family; Talcott, George Henry, -1854.; Talcott, S. V. (Sebastian Visscher), 1812-; United States. Army. Ordnance Department; Mexican War (1846-1848)
Subjects:
Surveying -- Ohio.; Surveying -- Kentucky.; Surveying -- Tennessee.; Families -- New York (State); Families -- Illinois.; Families -- Connecticut.; Families -- England.; Decedents' estates.; Boundaries; Families; Surveying; Surveyors.
Places:
Mexican War, 1846-1848.; Connecticut; England; Illinois; Kentucky; New York (State); Ohio; Tennessee
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Legal documents
  - Will of John Talcott, 1604-09-11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Extracted from the Registry of the Prerogative Court of Canterbury."
    Braintree, England
  - Inventory of John Talcott Estate, 1660-06-04 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Hartford, Connecticut
  - Will of Dorothy Talcott, widow of John Talcott, 1669-09-22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Inventory of Estate
  - Inventory of Lieut. Col. John Talcott Estate, 1688-07-23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Will of Capt. Samuel Talcott, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Inventory
    Wethersfield, Connecticut
  - Will of Lieut. Benjamin Talcott, 1727 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Glastenbury
  - Will of Jonathan Shearman, 1778-03-23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    South Kingston, Kings County, Rhode Island
  - Certificate- 10 shares in the US Lombard Assoc. for George Talcott., 1825-07-01 (Box 2)
  - Deed from Alexander Seymour and Sands Higginbotham to Robert Sherman for Watts Sherman's estate, 1827-01-12 (Box 2)
  - Revised last will of Robert Sherman., 1829-12-07 (Box 2)
  - Robert Sherman and Samuel Thomson partnership agreement "partners in trade under firm of Sherman and Thomson.", 1830-03-24 (Box 2)
  - Honor Sherman's authorization for Thomas S. Taylor to lease her real estate in Rhode Island (town of Exeter) and transact her business., 1830-07-23 (Box 2)
  - Samuel Thomson signs over to Robert Sherman his right title and interest in and to the partnership debts, full power to collect and receive debts. 2- Accounts of debts to be collected and received., 1830-03-10-1831 (Box 2)
  - [Bond] - Samuel Thomson breaks partnership with Robert Sherman and turns over all his rights and interests in the firm., 1831-03-10 (Box 2)
  - Will of Robert Sherman, Jr. (daughter- Olivia Sherman), 1827-02-03 (Box 2)
  - Above will of Robert Sherman, Jr. Cancelled.1- deprived by Samuel Thomson of the means of willing anything to anybody., 1831-03-23 (Box 2)
  - Agreement: W. Barron Williams rents from Robert Sherman a 2-story store on Carrole St. in Rochester., 1830-04-23 (Box 2)
  - Williams receives 2,000 from R. Sherman in settlement with account in the agreement., 1831-04-23 (Box 2)
  - Account of W.P. Sherman Estate (William Pitt [?]), 1832-01-01 (Box 2)
  - Bond of Robert Sherman to Willette H. Sherman the sum of 4 thousand., 1832-01-01 (Box 2)
  - Bond of R. Sherman to Willette H. Sherman the sum of nine thousand., 1832-01-01 (Box 2)
  - Bond R. Sherman to Jonathan Sherman the sum of 2,000., 1832-01-10 (Box 2)
  - Bond R. Sherman to Jonathan Sherman the sum of 2,000., 1832-01-10 (Box 2)
  - R. Sherman in account with W. Barron Williams., 1832-03-08 (Box 2)
  - Williams' promise to pay R. Sherman $414.56 after 13 months., 1832-04-10 (Box 2)
  - Letter from Hon. Lew Cass (?), Department of War, Washington D.C. to Mayor George Talcott., 1832-05-25 (Box 2)
    "Requesting suggestions for altercation [alteration?] in military code."
  - Williams' promise to pay Sherman 242.45 after 4 months., 1832-09-13 (Box 2)
  - Account of back debts of late firm of Sherman and Thomson., 1832-09-10 (Box 2)
  - Statement of property purchases of Robert Sherman., 1832-09-10 (Box 2)
  - Statement of indebtedness of Samuel Lizer to R. Sherman and Bob Jones (about 200 dollars.), 1832-10-30 (Box 2)
  - Elisha Cary turns over all right, title and interest in the lumber at rear of Henry Seymour's lot., 1832-11-22 (Box 2)
  - Sherriff's certificate stating sale of land (Utica) owned by Abby Jane Flandreau in favor of Robert Sherman., 1833-01-23 (Box 2)
  - Robert Sherman transfers to EBEN B. Sherman the right to collect and receive the debts and notes of his accounts for endorsing his 6 promisory notes which total 2,928.86. Also account., 1833-07-01 (Box 2)
  - Letter to daughter Olivia Sherman from Robert Sherman, 1833-07-19 (Box 2)
    R.S. illness
  - W.B. Williams notes due to R. Sherman, 1833-08-19 (Box 2)
  - W.B. Williams notes endorsed to Robert S., 1833-04-10-1833-04-13 (Box 2)
  - Gideon Sherman and wife give up all rights and titles to Robert Sherman's will to inherit his real estate when R.S.'s wife, Honor, dies. Gideonson of R.S. of Rhode Island., 1834 (Box 2)
  - 2 Bills of R. Sherman (for nails, shoes for horse, etc.), 1835 (Box 2)
  - 25 week subscription to Utica Observer R.S., 1835-07-28 (Box 2)
  - Bills of R.S. for misc. material (and recetpts), 1835, 1836 (Box 2)
  - Bill of Deborah Rowland for 32.20 to the late firm of Sherman and Thomson., 1837-01-01 (Box 2)
  - Utica E.B. Sherman informs Olivia Sherman of death of her father, Robert., 1838-07-07 (Box 2)
  - Diary kept by Sebastian Vischer Talcott, son of George Talcott of Albany. He married Olivia Sherman, daughter of Robert Sherman., 1841-04-28-1842-08-27; Green leather (Box 3)
  - Utica Certificate giving Willett H. Sherman the letters of Administration of the Robert Sherman Estate, 1838-12-26 (Box 3)
  - Surrogate Letter of Administration on the personal Estate of R.S. to W.H.S., 1838-12-26 (Box 3)
  - Inventory of R.S. estate (personal property) by W.H. Sherman, 1839-01-07 (Box 3)
  - Accounts of R.S. estate., 1839-06-1839-09-07 (Box 3)
  - Lara Sherman as widow of R.S. releases all claims of estate to W.H. Sherman, 1839-10-05 (Box 3)
  - Map 1) disputed territory upper N.Y. lower Canada, 1839 (Box 3)
  - 40- Bill and receipts of R.S. estate., 1839 (Box 3)
- Letters
  - Toriee Goodrich, Charles Dickinson, and Jedediah Waterman form co-partnership in a ship chancellory line., 1802-12-20 (Box 1)
  - receipts, bills, letters of attorney., Undated (Box 1)
  - 2 letters. War of 1812., 1812-07-10 (Box 1)
    George Talcott begs G.T. Jr. to come home to Glastenbury before the British fleet gets him.
  - Letters from Angelica Talcott (wife) to George Talcott, 1816-06-26-1816-08-13 (Box 1)
  - Letters (inventories) by Sherman., Undated (Box 1)
  - Letter to Capt. Talcott from J. Miller Byent (?), 1817-07-07 (Box 1)
    Letter to Capt. Talcott from J. Miller Byent (?) asking Talcott for permission to have the President use his horse.
  - Watts Sherman: accounts- receipts and expenditures, accounts of Estate, 1819-08-27-1820-08-31 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Isaac H. Bogart from George Talcott, 1820-12-18 (Box 1)
    Subject: Burning of steamboat; boilers explode, narrow escape for George and Angelica and children
  - Accounts for Estate in New York, 1821-01-31 (Box 1)
  - Maria Sherman- one of the executors of Watts Sherman Estate, 1821-01-31 (Box 1)
  - Will of Watts Sherman (New York City) Inventory of Estate, 1822-04-05 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Maria Sherman from Olivia Sherman, 1822-08-05 (Box 1)
  - Account of Watts Sherman Estate, 1822-11-06 (Box 1)
  - 2 letters to Maria Shearman from Robert (husband), 1822-11-17 (Box 1)
  - Amanda L. Sherman Account, 1823-02-18 (Box 1)
  - Opinions on Will of. Watts Sherman by Judge Jonas Platt, 1823-05-26 (Box 1)
  - Opinion of Joseph Kirkland., Undated (Box 1)
  - George Talcott- US Army surveyor Diary, 1823-06; brown leather cover, string clasp (Box 1)
    Tennessee - Kentucky
  - 2 letters of Administration on the estates of Olivia and Lucy A. Sherman. Administrator: Robert Shearman, 1823-09-17 (Box 2)
  - Personal property record of Watts Sherman, 1824-09-08 (Box 2)
  - 2 Accounts of Watts Sherman Estate, 1824-09-08 (Box 2)
  - Certificate to George Talcott for degree of Master Mason, 1824 (Box 2)
    Lawrenceville, Pennsylvania
  - E.B. Sherman lease to James H. Hackett- for 2 years from May 1, 1825, land and buildings in Utica- Genesee St., 1825-05-01 (Box 2)
  - Deed of above land from E.B. Sherman and wife Sarah to Robert Sherman, 1825-09-01 (Box 2)
  - Lease from Thomas S. Taylor- Robert Sherman, 1826-12-15 (Box 2)
  - Letter from Robert Sherman to Alexander Seymour and Sands Higinbotham, 1823-09-30 (Box 2)
    About Inventory of Olivia and Lucy Sherman from their executer of Watts Sherman Estate.
  - Letter to Mrs. Robert Sherman (Maria) from Robert, 1823-11-15 (Box 2)
    About search for Jane Wilson and the meeting of friends.
  - Will of Robert Sherman, 1823-11-23 (Box 2)
    Rhode Island
  - Watts Sherman Estate Account, 1824-02-28 (Box 2)
  - Letter to Joshua Hathaway, Esquire (Surrogate of County of Oneida from Robert Sherman), 1824-03-17 (Box 2)
    Statement and report of the Olivia and Lucy Sherman estate.
  - Letter to Robert Sherman from Maria Sherman, 1824-09-24 (Box 2)
    About illness of Maria
  - Letter to Mrs. Robert Sherman form Mr. H. Author, 1824-10-20 (Box 2)
    About Maria's illness and profession of faith in God.
  - Letter to Mr. R. Sherman from B.B. Lansing, 1824-12-22 (Box 2)
    Utica business.
  - Letter to Lieut. Col. Talcott from Winfield Scott, 1842-02-14 (Box 3)
    subject: Mr. Benton's machine (invention) for throwing shots (balls)
  - letter to Col. Talcott from Andrew Meneely, 1842-05-17 (Box 3)
    "wants to sell levelling and surveying instruments to government--- asks Talcott to help him."
    West Troy Albany, New York
  - Letter 2 invitations to Col. Talcott to visit the US ship "Princeton" at Greenleap Point(?) from Capt. R.F. Stockton., 1844-02-14 (Box 3)
  - Personal letters to Olivia Sherman Talcott from E.B. Sherman Utica, 1844 (Box 3)
  - Letter to E.B. Sherman from Olivia Talcott "wants settlement papers of father's estate and advice on selling grandfathers farm to Cousin Joseph.", Undated (Box 3)
  - Account of R.S. estate sent to Olivia Talcott, 1845-02-01 (Box 3)
  - Letter to S.V. Talcott Account of R.S. estate, 1845-02-26 (Box 3)
  - Letter to Col. Talcott from James Baldwin, 1845-11-15 (Box 3)
    Subject: school tax in district; money used to build a school.
  - Letter to Col. Talcott from W.H. Sherman, 1846-01-17 (Box 3)
    Subject: administration of R.S. Estate also farm in Rhode Island.
  - Estate R.S. to Estate E.B. Sherman., 1846-03-21 (Box 3)
  - Estate R.S. To estate W.H. Sherman., 1846-03-21 (Box 3)
  - Letter to S.V. Talcott from W.H. Sherman, 1846-06-01 (Box 3)
    Subject: selling farm in Rhode Island to cousin Joseph, investigation of funds paid by R.S. to Mrs. Holchetrass (?) a larger amount than entitled to receive.
  - Letter to S.V. Talcott from Mr. Duncan, 1846-10-21 (Box 3)
    Subject: value of farm in Rhode Island worth 300.
  - Letter to S.V. Talcott from James Buchanan introducing Charles Kugler Esq., 1847-11-10 (Box 3)
    Washington
  - Letter to S.V. Talcott from W.H. Seward, 1850-01-26 (Box 3)
    Subject: introducing Babcock who has invented a new combination of metals.
  - The Sherman family line, 1851 (Box 3)
  - Redemption of real estate taxes. Andrew Hale turns over right to land to S.V. Talcott., 1856-07-28 (Box 3)
    Danville, Illinois
  - Letter from Major Craig to John F. Lee, 1846-12-13 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letter from John F. Lee to George Talcott, 1846-12-31 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letter from A. B. Dyer to George Talcott, 1847-02-17 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-02-20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-02-27 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-03-09 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-03-20 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-03-25 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-03-28 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-03-30 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Letter from A. B. Dyer to George Talcott, 1847-04-01 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-04-05 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-04-08 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Letter from W. W. S. Bliss to George D. Ramsay, 1847-04-10 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Letter from George Ramsay to George Talcott, 1847-04-20 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-04-28 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-05-18 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-05-21 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Letter from J. Gorgas to A. R. Hetzel, 1847-05-29 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-06-04 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Letter from J. Gorgas to A. R. Hetzel, 1847-06-05 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Letter from J. Gorgas to A. R. Hetzel, 1847-06-09 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-08-06 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Letter from A. B. Dyer to George Talcott, 1847-08-11 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Letter from B. M. Byrne to George Ramsay, 1847-08-25 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Letter from J. Gorgas (but initialed by "SM'') to George Talcott, 1847-08-26 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-08-27 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Letter from George Ramsay to George Talcott, 1847-08-31 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to Maj. Gen. Worth, 1847-09-15 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-09-27 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-09-27 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-10-07 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-10-27 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1847-12-08 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Letter from Benj. Huger to George Talcott, 1848-01-13 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Letter from A. B. Dyer to George Talcott, 1848-04-06 (Box 4, Folder 36)